# Ryan Parman • jobs@ryanparman.com

Cloud-native engineering leader with a focus on reliability, scalability, and security for the modern web.

Links: GitHub (personal) • GitHub (side project) • LinkedIn • Stack Overflow • Role-targeted résumés

Format: Web • PDF • Word • OpenDocument

### Summary

Ryan Parman is a cloud-native engineering leader with over 25 years of experience, who specializes in technical leadership, software development, site reliability engineering, and cybersecurity for the modern web. Excels at listening, adapting, and driving continuous improvement. Delivers exceptional work, builds impactful solutions, and elevates team performance.

## **Work Experience**

Older roles are truncated for brevity. If interested, details can be found on GitHub.

# McGraw Hill — Remote (since COVID), previously Seattle, WA

#### Principal Engineer, Cloud Center of Excellence (January 2024—October 2024)

- Joined a team whose mission was to provide guidance and support in the cloud journey of the entire organization.
- · Proposed best practices, guardrails, and security measures to ensure a secure and efficient cloud environment.
- Identified opportunities to extend the security measures and guardrails devised for AWS to other cloud platforms.

#### Principal Cloud and Platform Engineer (June 2020—January 2024)

- Partnered with Enterprise Architecture and <u>AWS Professional Services</u> to deploy <u>Control Tower</u> and <u>Identity Center</u>, resulting in lowered costs and increased control over account guardrails.
- Managed the Base AMI program. Leveraged insights from CIS, security patching, and internal needs to develop a unified build pipeline
  integrating best practices.
- Conducted comprehensive scans of <u>Route 53</u> to obtain a mapping of the company's thousands of active websites. Prioritized identifying and remediating misconfigurations, rotating certificates, and increasing visibility.
- Implemented the Linux runtime environment used by self-hosted GitHub Actions runners.
- Spearheaded the <u>Artifactory</u> Rebuild project. Ran the project from inception to completion, including the majority of development. Directed effort across ~80 teams and ~300 services to complete the project.
- Improved security by enabling continuous token and password rotation for engineering teams by building a Token Vending Machine.
- Resolved all technology blockers preventing migration lower-cost ARM64 CPUs, opening the door for ~\$450k/year in cost savings.
- Led dozens of smaller projects, offered guidance to engineers on best practices, and documented knowledge.

#### **Engineering Manager, Site Reliability (October 2018—June 2020)**

- Led the <u>Site Reliability Engineering</u> (SRE) team in addressing macro-oriented problems affecting engineering teams, empowering greater self-service.
- Established a process for maintaining reusable <u>Terraform</u> modules which teams leveraged to compose infrastructure with minimal effort.
- Customized the <u>Amazon Linux</u> AMIs to comply with Level-2 <u>CIS</u> Guidelines for both Amazon Linux and <u>Docker</u>. Liaised with cybersecurity, operations, and business units to ensure compliance.
- Invented custom security and operational tooling to understand the current posture of ~200 AWS accounts where off-the-shelf tools did not meet the needs of the organization.
- Reduced the time to deploy a new service from dozens of weeks to a single meeting by implementing a Monitoring-as-Code
  methodology, and defining broad-use Service Level Objectives (SLOs).

- Led the development of Tier-1 services within the educational content authoring pipeline, leveraging technologies such as <u>REST</u>,
   <u>GraphQL</u>, API design, <u>Amazon ECS</u> (similar to <u>Kubernetes</u>), <u>Docker</u>, <u>Terraform</u>, <u>ePubs</u>, and security best practices.
- Led the development of the authoring component of the <u>SmartBook 2.0 product</u>, and the internal system which indexes authored content, builds ePubs, and encodes images/video for the ePub CDN using <u>ffmpeg</u>.
- Established the technical direction of these projects, promoted adoption across the organization, published comprehensive documentation, and offered ongoing integration guidance.
- Accelerated the adoption of CI/CD, rapid deployment practices, and Docker containers, shortening the feedback loop for developers
  and increasing the reliability of deployments.
- Served as a core resource in adopting Infrastructure-as-Code (IaC) tools such as Terraform and Packer.

### WePay — Redwood City, CA

#### DevOps Engineer (April 2015—September 2016)

- Led a cross-company initiative to upgrade the monolithic application from <a href="PHP">PHP</a> 5.4 to PHP 5.6 (the latest at the time). Facilitated cross-team collaboration among all major engineering teams and QA departments to achieve results.
- Initiated a program to automate the creation of base server images for cloud servers. This allowed new servers to boot and begin serving traffic ~75% faster.
- Invested in monitoring and alerting systems to prevent customer-facing issues.
- Increased reliability and efficiency by implementing configuration-as-code for cloud infrastructure in GCP.

### Senior API Engineer (April 2014—April 2015)

- Led the company's HackerOne program, coordinating across teams to address security issues.
- Built a development environment for engineering teams. Reduced new engineer onboarding time from 2 weeks to 1 day.
- Expanded WePay's payment security offerings by designing MFA-as-a-Service (U.S. patent filing <u>US15042104</u>).

#### Amazon Web Services — Seattle, WA

#### Web Development Engineer II (March 2010—April 2014)

- Created the <u>AWS SDK for PHP</u>, enabled AWS to reach the largest developer group <u>PHP</u>.
- Initiated the creation of AWS SDK for PHP v2 to address changes in the PHP language and growth of AWS services.
- Led one of the first teams to provide reusable UI building blocks for the <u>AWS Management Console</u>, by collaborating directly with the AWS Design team.
- Invested in increased transparency, better communication, and improved tooling for developers. [Examples]

#### **Projects**

Proof that I can code, call APIs, interact with SDKs, and build user-facing software. I have live-coding anxiety, so live-coding interviews will always present me at my worst, not my best.

- **DevSec Tools:** Building a <u>website</u>, <u>CLI tool, and Go library</u> for helping developers identify potential web security configuration issues (in-progress).
- Custom Linux Packages: Building a repository of custom Linux packages (in-progress).
- CSP Evaluator: Building a parser and evaluator for Content Security Policy (CSP) directives in Go (in-progress).
- Terraform Provider: Built a custom provider which provides a set of utility functions for use in Terraform/OpenTofu.
- Multi-Platform Docker: Built a downloader for GitHub release assets which simplifies building multi-platform images.
- AWS Organization Security: Built a <u>library + CLI tool</u> which simplifies the AWS pattern for multi-account organizations which they call "hub and spoke."

- AWS Session Manager: The terminal is the right tool for shell sessions. Built a <u>TUI</u> for <u>simplifying connections to SSM-enabled EC2</u> <u>instances</u> using your Terminal.
- Configuration for tflint: Built a tool for generating up-to-date configurations for AWS/GCP/Azure for use with tflint.

#### Recommendations

See a <u>selective list of recommendations</u> from co-workers and peers.

# **Groups and Accomplishments**

- U.S. patent filing, "System and Methods for User Authentication across Multiple Domains" (US15042104) (2016)
- U.S. patent filing, "Hive-based Peer-to-Peer Network" (US8103870B2) (2007)
- Voting representative for AWS, <u>PHP Framework Interoperability Group</u> (2012–2013)

### **Skills**

This list is not exhaustive, but these are software and skills I leveraged in the roles above which are most relevant to Cloud Engineering, DevOps, and Site Reliability Engineering roles.

TLS and cipher suites, ACM, ARM64, AWS Well-Architected, Ansible, Artifactory, Bash, Bash, CIS, CentOS, CloudFront, Control Tower, Docker, EC2, ECS, GCP, GitHub Actions, GitHub Enterprise, Git, Go, Identity Center, Image Builder, Lambda, Nginx, OpenTofu, PHP, Packer, Python, RDS Aurora, Redis, Route 53, S3, SDKs, Secrets Manager, Terraform, automation, cloud configuration security, multi-platform development, operational reliability, performance, scalability.

#### **Education**

Silicon Valley College (now Carrington College), San Jose, CA. Bachelor of Arts, Design and Visualization